<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-rtgwg-ni-model-01" >

<front>
<title abbrev="YANG NIs">YANG Network Instances</title>
    <author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger'>
     <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
     <address>
       <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='C.' surname="Hopps" fullname='Christan Hopps'>
    <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
     <address>
       <email>chopps@chopps.org</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>301 Midenhall Way</street>
        <city>Cary</city> <region>NC</region>
        <country>USA</country>
        <code>27513</code>
       </postal>
       <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='D.' surname="Bogdanovic" fullname='Dean Bogdanovic'>
    <organization></organization>
     <address>
       <email>ivandean@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <date/>
  <abstract>
<t>
  This document defines a network instance module. This module along
  with the logical network element module can be used to manage the
  logical and virtual resource representations that may be present on a
  network device. Examples of common industry terms for logical resource
  representations are Logical Systems or Logical Routers. Examples of
  common industry terms for virtual resource representations are Virtual
  Routing and Forwarding (VRF) instances and Virtual Switch Instances
  (VSIs).
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="sec-1" title="Introduction">
<t>
   This document defines the second of two new modules that are defined
   to support the configuration and operation of network-devices that
   allow for the partitioning of resources from both, or either,
   management and networking perspectives.  Both make use of the
   YANG functionality enabled by YANG Schema Mount <xref
   target="I-D.ietf-netmod-schema-mount"/>.  
</t>
<t>
   Two forms of resource partitioning are supported:
</t>
<t>
   The first form, which is defined in <xref target="LNE-MODEL"/>,
   provides a logical partitioning of a network device where each
   partition is separately managed as essentially an independent
   network element which is 'hosted' by the base network device.
   These hosted network elements are referred to as logical
   network elements, or LNEs, and are supported by the
   logical-network-element module defined in <xref target="LNE-MODEL"/>.
   The module is used to identify LNEs and associate resources from the
   network-device with each LNE.  LNEs themselves are represented
   in YANG as independent network devices; each accessed
   independently.  Optionally, and when supported by the
   implementation, they may also be accessed from the host system.
   Examples of vendor terminology for an LNE include logical
   system or logical router, and virtual switch, chassis, or fabric.
</t>
<t>
   The second form, which is defined in this document, provides
   support what is commonly referred to as Virtual Routing and
   Forwarding (VRF) instances as well as Virtual Switch Instances
   (VSI), see <xref target="RFC4026"/>.  In this form of resource
   partitioning multiple control plane and forwarding/bridging
   instances are provided by and managed via a single (physical or
   logical) network device.  This form of resource partitioning is
   referred to as Network Instances and are supported by the
   network-instance module defined below.  Configuration and
   operation of each network-instance is always via the network
   device and the network-instance module.
</t>
<t>
   This document was motivated by, and derived from,
   <xref target="RTG-DEVICE-MODEL"/>.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-1.1" title="Status of Work and Open Issues">
<t>
The top open issues are:
  <list style="numbers">
   <t>This document will need to match the evolution and
   standardization of  <xref target="I-D.openconfig-netmod-opstate"/> or
   <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-opstate-reqs"/> by the Netmod WG.
   </t>
   </list>
 </t>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-2" title="Overview">
<t>
   In this document, we consider network devices that support protocols
   and functions defined within the IETF Routing Area, e.g, routers,
   firewalls and hosts. Such devices may be physical or virtual, e.g., a
   classic router with custom hardware or one residing within a
   server-based virtual machine implementing a virtual network function
   (VNF). Each device may sub-divide their resources into logical
   network elements (LNEs) each of which provides a managed logical
   device.  Examples of vendor terminology for an LNE include logical
   system or logical router, and virtual switch, chassis, or fabric. Each
   LNE may also support virtual routing and forwarding (VRF) and virtual
   switching instance (VSI) functions, which are referred to below as a
   network instances (NIs). This breakdown is represented in
   Figure 1.
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>

           ,''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''''`.
           |      Network Device (Physical or Virtual)     |
           | .....................   ..................... |
           | :  Logical Network  :   :  Logical Network  : |
           | :      Element      :   :      Element      : |
           | :+-----+-----+-----+:   :+-----+-----+-----+: |
           | :| Net | Net | Net |:   :| Net | Net | Net |: |
           | :|Inst.|Inst.|Inst.|:   :|Inst.|Inst.|Inst.|: |
           | :+-----+-----+-----+:   :+-----+-----+-----+: |
           | :  | |   | |   | |  :   :  | |   | |   | |  : |
           | :..|.|...|.|...|.|..:   :..|.|...|.|...|.|..: |
           |    | |   | |   | |         | |   | |   | |    |
            `'''|'|'''|'|'''|'|'''''''''|'|'''|'|'''|'|'''''
                | |   | |   | |         | |   | |   | |
                   Interfaces              Interfaces
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
                 Figure 1: Module Element Relationships
</t>
<t>
   A model for LNEs is described in <xref target="LNE-MODEL"/> and
   the model for network instances is covered in <xref
   target="sec-NI"/>.  For more information on how these models
   may be used within an overall device model structure, see <xref
   target="RTG-DEVICE-MODEL"/>.
</t>
<t>
   The interface management model <xref target="RFC7223"/> is an
   existing model that is impacted by the definition of LNEs and
   network instances.  This document and <xref target="LNE-MODEL"/>
   define augmentations to the interface module to support LNEs
   and NIs.  Similar elements, although perhaps only for LNEs, may
   also need to be included as part of the definition of the
   future hardware and QoS modules.
</t>
<t>
   Interfaces are a crucial part of any network device's
   configuration and operational state.  They generally include a
   combination of raw physical interfaces, link-layer interfaces,
   addressing configuration, and logical interfaces that may not
   be tied to any physical interface.  Several system services,
   and layer 2 and layer 3 protocols may also associate
   configuration or operational state data with different types of
   interfaces (these relationships are not shown for simplicity).
   The interface management model is defined by <xref
   target="RFC7223"/>.
</t>
<t>
   The logical-network-element and network-instance modules
   augment the existing interface management model in two ways:
   The first, by the logical-network-element module, adds an
   identifier which is used on physical interface types to
   identify an associated LNE.  The second, by the
   network-instance module, adds a name which is used on
   interface or sub-interface types to identify an associated 
   network instance.
   Similarly, this name is also added for IPv4 and IPv6 types, as
   defined in <xref target="RFC7277"/>.
</t>
<t>
   The interface related augmentations are as follows:
<figure>
<artwork>
    module: ietf-logical-network-element
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface:
       +--rw bind-lne-name?   string

    module: ietf-network-instance
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv4:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv6:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
   The following is an example of envisioned combined usage.  The
   interfaces container includes a number of commonly used
   components as examples:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
          +--rw if:interfaces
          |  +--rw interface* [name]
          |     +--rw name                       string
          |     +--rw bind-lne-name?             string
          |     +--rw ethernet
          |     |  +--rw ni:bind-network-instance-name? string
          |     |  +--rw aggregates
          |     |  +--rw rstp
          |     |  +--rw lldp
          |     |  +--rw ptp
          |     +--rw vlans
          |     +--rw tunnels
          |     +--rw ipv4
          |     |  +--rw ni:bind-network-instance-name? string
          |     |  +--rw arp
          |     |  +--rw icmp
          |     |  +--rw vrrp
          |     |  +--rw dhcp-client
          |     +--rw ipv6
          |        +--rw ni:bind-network-instance-name? string
          |        +--rw vrrp
          |        +--rw icmpv6
          |        +--rw nd
          |        +--rw dhcpv6-client
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
   The <xref target="RFC7223"/> defined interface model is
   structured to include all interfaces in a flat list, without
   regard to logical or virtual instances (e.g., VRFs) supported
   on the device.  The bind-lne-name and
   bind-network-instance-name leaves provide the association
   between an interface and its associated LNE and NI (e.g., VRF
   or VSI).
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-NI" title="  Network Instances">
<t>
   The network instance container is used to represent virtual routing
   and forwarding instances (VRFs) and virtual switching instances
   (VSIs), <xref target="RFC4026"/>.  VRFs and VSIs are commonly used to isolate
   routing and switching domains, for example to create virtual private
   networks, each with their own active protocols and routing/switching
   policies.  The model represents both core/provider and virtual
   instances.  Network instances reuse and build on <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-routing-cfg"/>
   and are shown below:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    module: ietf-network-instance
       +--rw network-instances
          +--rw network-instance* [name]
             +--rw name                         string
             +--rw type?                        identityref
             +--rw enabled?                     boolean
             +--rw description?                 string
             +--rw network-instance-policy
             |  ...
             +--rw root?                      yang-schema-mount
             |  ...
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv4:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
    augment /if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv6:
       +--rw bind-network-instance-name?   string
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
   A network instance is identified by a
   `name` string.  This string is used both as
   an index within the network-instance module and to associate
   resources with a network instance as shown above in the
   interface augmentation. Type is used to indicate the type NI,
   such as L3-VRF, VPLS, L2-VSI, etc. Network instance policy
   and root are discussed in greater detail below.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-NI.1" title="  Network Instance Policy">
<t>
   Network instance policies are used to control how NI
   information is represented at the device level, VRF routing
   policies, and VRF/VSI identifiers. Examples include BGP route
   targets (RTs) and route distinguishers (RDs), virtual network
   identifiers (VN-IDs), VPLS neighbors, etc. The structure is
   expected to be:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    module: ietf-network-instance
       +--rw network-instances
          +--rw network-instance* [name]
             +--rw network-instance-policy
                (TBD)
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-NI.2" title="  Network Instance Management">
<t>
   Modules that may be used to represent network instance
   specific information will be available under
   `root`.  As with LNEs, actual module
   availability is expected to be implementation dependent. The
   yang library module <xref target="I-D.ietf-netconf-yang-library"/>
   is expected to be the primary method
   used to identify supported modules.  Resource related control
   and assignment is expected to be managed at the network-device
   level, not the network instance level, based on the
   `bind-network-instance-name` augmentation
   mentioned above.
</t>
<t>
   As an example, consider the case where a network instance with
   a `name` of "green" is defined on a network
   device.  In this case the following structure might be made
   available:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
   +--rw yanglib:modules-state           [I-D.ietf-netconf-yang-library]
   +--rw if:interfaces                   [RFC7223]
   |  +--rw bind-network-instance-name="green" string
   +--rw network-instances
      +--rw network-instance* [name]
         +--rw name="green"    string
         +--rw type?                           identityref
         +--rw enabled=true                    boolean
         +--rw description="The Green VRF"     string
         +--rw network-instance-policy
         |  ... (RT=1000:1, RD=1.2.3.4)
         +--rw root?                           yang-schema-mount
            +--rw yanglib:modules-state  [I-D.ietf-netconf-yang-library]
            +--rw if:intefaces           [RFC7223]
            +--rw mm:network-services
            +--rw nn:oam-protocols
            +--rw oo:routing
            +--rw pp:mpls
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
    All modules that represent control-plane and data-plane
    information may be present at the `root`,
    and be accessible via paths modified per
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-schema-mount"/>.  The list of available
    modules is expected to be implementation dependent.  As is the
    method used by an implementation to support NIs.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-NI.3" title="  Network Instance Instantiation">
  <t>
    Network instances may be controlled by clients using existing list
    operations.  When list entries are created, a new instance is
    instantiated. The models mounted under a NI root is expected to be
    dependent on the server implementation.  When a list entry is
    deleted, an existing network instance is destroyed. For more
    information see <xref target="RFC7950"/> Section 7.8.6.
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-4" title="  Security Considerations">
  <t>
    TBD
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-5" title="  IANA Considerations">
  <t>
    This document registers a URI in the IETF XML registry <xref
    target="RFC3688"/>.  Following the format in RFC 3688, the following
    registration is requested to be made.
  </t>
  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
     URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-network-instance

     Registrant Contact: The IESG.

     XML: N/A, the requested URI is an XML namespace.
     ]]></artwork>
  </figure>
  <t>
    This document registers a YANG module in the YANG Module Names
    registry <xref target="RFC6020"/>.
  </t>
  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  name:        ietf-network-instance
  namespace:   urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-network-instance
  prefix:      ni
  reference:   RFC XXXX
  ]]></artwork>
  </figure>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-6.3" title="  Network Instance Model">
<t>
   The structure of the model defined in this document is described
   by the YANG module below.
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-network-instance@2016-10-27.yang"
module ietf-network-instance {

  yang-version 1.1;

  // namespace
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-network-instance";

  prefix ni;

  // import some basic types
  import ietf-interfaces {
    prefix if;
  }

  import ietf-ip {
    prefix ip;
  }

  import ietf-yang-schema-mount {
    prefix yangmnt;
  }

// meta
  organization "IETF Routing Area Working Group (rtgwg)";

  contact
      "Routing Area Working Group - <rtgwg@ietf.org>";

  description
    "This module is used to support multiple network instances
     within a single physical or virtual device.  Network
     instances are commonly know as VRFs (virtual routing
     and forwarding) and VSIs (virtual switching instances).";

  revision "2016-10-27" {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference "RFC TBD";
  }

  // extension statements

  feature bind-network-instance-name {
    description
      "Network Instance to which an interface instance is bound";
  }

  // identity statements

  identity network-instance-type {
      description
         "Base identity from which identities describing
          network instance types are derived.";
  }

   identity ipv4-interface-protocol-type {
      description
          "Base identity for derivation of IPv4 interface
           protocols";
   }

   identity ipv6-interface-protocol-type {
      description
          "Base identity for derivation of IPv6 interface
           protocols";
   }

  // typedef statements

  // grouping statements

  grouping interface-ip-common {
    description
      "interface-specific configuration for IP interfaces, IPv4 and
      IPv6";

  }

  grouping ipv4-interface-protocols {
      container ipv4-interface-protocols {
          list ipv4-interface-protocol {
              key "type";
              leaf type {
                  type identityref {
                      base ipv4-interface-protocol-type;
                  }
                  mandatory true;
                  description
                      "ARP, ICMP, VRRP, DHCP Client, etc.";
              }
              description
                  "List of IPv4 protocols configured
                   on an interface";
          }
          description
              "Container for list of IPv4 protocols configured
                on an interface";
      }
      description
          "Grouping for IPv4 protocols configured on an interface";
  }

  grouping ipv6-interface-protocols {
      description
          "Grouping for IPv6 protocols configured on
           an interface.";
      container ipv6-interface-protocols {
          description
              "Container for list of IPv6 protocols configured
                on an interface.";
          list ipv6-interface-protocol {
              key "type";
              description
                  "List of IPv6 protocols configured
                   on an interface";
              leaf type {
                  type identityref {
                      base ipv6-interface-protocol-type;
                  }
                  mandatory true;
                  description
                      "ND, ICMPv6, VRRP, DHCPv6 Client, etc.";
              }
          }
      }
  }

  grouping network-instance-policy {
    description
        "Network instance policies such as route
         distinguisher, route targets, VPLS ID and neighbor,
         Ethernet ID, etc. ";
    reference
        "RFC 4364 - BGP/MPLS Virtual Private Networks (VPNs)
         RFC 6074 - Provisioning, Auto-Discovery, and Signaling
              in Layer 2 Virtual Private Networks (L2VPNs)
         RFC 7432 - BGP MPLS-Based Ethernet VPN";
    container network-instance-policy {
        description
          "Network Instance Policy -- details TBD, 
          perhaps based on BESS model";
    }
  }

  // top level device definition statements
  container network-instances {
      description "Network instances each of which have
                   an independent IP/IPv6 addressing space
                   and protocol instantiations. For layer 3,
                   this consistent with the routing-instance
                   definition in ietf-routing";
      reference "draft-ietf-netmod-routing-cfg";
      list network-instance {
          key name;
          description "List of network-instances";
          leaf name {
              type string;
              description "device scoped
                           identifier for the network
                           instance";
          }
          leaf type {
              type identityref {
                  base network-instance-type;
              }
              description
                  "The network instance type -- details TBD
                   Likely types include core, L3-VRF, VPLS,
                   L2-cross-connect, L2-VSI, etc.";
          }
          leaf enabled {
              type boolean;
              default "true";
              description
                "Flag indicating whether or not the network
                 instance is enabled.";
          }
          leaf description {
              type string;
              description
                "Description of the network instance
                and its intended purpose";
          }

          uses network-instance-policy;

          anydata root {
              yangmnt:mount-point root;
              description "Root for models supported per
                           network instance";
          }
      }
  }

  // augment statements

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface" {
    description
        "Add a node for the identification of the logical network
        instance (which is within the interface's identified logical
        network element) associated with the IP information
        configured on an interface";

    leaf bind-network-instance-name {
      type string;
      description
        "Network Instance to which an interface is bound";
    }
  }

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv4" {
    description
        "Add a node for the identification of the logical
        network instance (which is within the interface's
        identified physical or virtual device) associated with
        the IP information configured on an interface";

    leaf bind-network-instance-name {
      type string;
      description
        "Network Instance to which IPv4 interface is bound";

    }
  }

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface/ip:ipv6" {
    description
        "Add a node for the identification of the logical
        network instance (which is within the interface's
        identified physical or virtual device) associated with
        the IP information configured on an interface";

    leaf bind-network-instance-name {
      type string;
      description
        "Network Instance to which IPv6 interface is bound";

    }
  }

  // rpc statements

  // notification statements

}
<CODE ENDS>
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>
</middle>

<?rfc needLines="20"?>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="LNE-MODEL">
<front>
<title>Logical Network Element Model</title>
<author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger'>
  <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
</author>
<author initials='C.' surname="Hopps" fullname='Christan Hopps'>
  <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
</author>
<author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials='D.' surname="Bogdanovic" fullname='Dean Bogdanovic'>
    <organization></organization>
</author>
<date month="October" year="2016" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-rtgwg-lne-model-01.txt"/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-netmod-schema-mount-02.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6020"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7223"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7277"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688"?>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="RTG-DEVICE-MODEL">
<front>
<title>Network Device YANG Organizational Models</title>
<author initials='A.' surname="Lindem" fullname='Acee Lindem' role='editor'>
  <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
</author>
<author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger' role='editor'>
  <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
</author>
<author initials='D.' surname="Bogdanovic" fullname='Dean Bogdanovic'>
    <organization></organization>
</author>
<author initials='C.' surname="Hopps" fullname='Christan Hopps'>
  <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
</author>
<date month="May" year="2016" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-rtgyangdt-rtgwg-device-model-04.txt"/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-openconfig-netmod-opstate-01.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-netmod-routing-cfg-24.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-netmod-opstate-reqs-04.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-netconf-yang-library-06.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4026"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>

</references>

<?rfc needLines="100"?>
<section title="Acknowledgments">
   <t>The Routing Area Yang Architecture design team members included Acee
   Lindem, Anees Shaikh, Christian Hopps, Dean Bogdanovic, Lou Berger,
   Qin Wu, Rob Shakir, Stephane Litkowski, and Yan Gang.</t>

  <t>The RFC text was produced using Marshall Rose's xml2rfc tool.
   <vspace blankLines="100"/></t>
</section>
<section title="Contributors">
<figure>
<artwork>
Contributors' Addresses

   TBD
</artwork>
</figure>
</section>
</back>

</rfc>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- fill-column:72 -->
<!-- End: -->
